So we've talked a lot about functions and have seen a few examples.
But as you know, the real learning happens in the doing.
So in this lesson we're going to create some functions of our own.
So to do this we are just going to get back to the basics by creating a new project.
I don't think I have to explain to you how to do that.
So with our new project created, as you can see, we have our classic cat sprite ready for action.
Now for this project we are going to do is something a little bit different and not just with functions.
We're going to make our cat draw with pens.
And yeah, I know it's pretty groundbreaking stuff.
So before we get into functions, you may be wondering how do I use this pen that you're speaking of?
Well, if you look right at the bottom, you will see this small button here.
Now, if you click it, you will see it brings up a bunch of different extensions that you can add to
your project, like music and camera, etc. and a lot of different ones that use external hardware.
Anyways, the one we are interested in is this drawer extension.
So clicking on it.
As you can see it adds this extra code group to our project and all these different code blocks that
are for the pen.
Now our project is going to be quite simple.
The cat is going to ask how many circles we must draw and then while it's going to draw them.
So to do this, we can grab a when flag clicked and then move to the sensing group.
Bring down this ask block.
Here we can just say how many circles shall I draw?
So if we click play, our cat asks how many circles it should draw.
We can enter in a number.
And of course, well, nothing happens.
So now what we're going to do is create a function that draws circles.
So moving down to my blocks here you can see we can click this option here to make a new block.
So this is where we can name our function I'll just call it a draw circle.
Then.
Remember how earlier I told you that some functions can have inputs while some don't?
Well, for our draw circle function we could just have it that we call it.
It just draws a single circle and that's that.
Or we could have it accept an input where we can choose how many circles we want to draw.
Just like with the example of the toy making machine, where we can decide if we want blue or red or
whatever color car.
In this case, we can decide for the function to accept an input, which will change the output that
the function creates.
So to do this, all we need to do is click this, add an input like so.
And as you can see at the top, we now have an input.
So I'll rename it to number of circles and then hit okay.
So now as you can see we now have this block right here.
And this is where we define our function.
So this is basically like we are building the machine telling it what it needs to do when it gets called.
So what we want our machine, or rather our function to do is draw circles.
So to draw a circle is quite simple.
All you need to do is put the pen down, then go over to motion and move ten steps.
Then turn 15 degrees and repeat this.
30 times like that.
So if you just click on this function you will see our cat draws a circle.
So that's cool and all.
But how do we use this function then.
Well, here we ask the user how many circles shall I draw to use this function?
All we need to do is grab this block draw circle underneath which calls our function.
And if we hit play and click this button.
As you can see, our cat draws a circle.
But of course there's a problem being our cat just draws one circle.
So this is where we need to tell the function how many circles it must draw.
So instead of leaving this blank, we can go to our sensing group and grab this answer block and use
it as an input.
So basically what this is doing is calling our draw circle function with the input entered in from the
user.
However, this still won't do anything because if you look at our function, we never tell the machine
what to do with the input it gets when it's being called.
So what we need to do is grab another repeat block and put all this inside.
And instead of entering in a value, we can grab this number of circles block and put it inside.
Now let's look at our script step by step so we can better understand.
Arquette asks how many circles to draw.
Let's say we enter in five circles.
We then call our circle drawing function with the number five as the input.
What this function does is it puts the pen down.
And then we have this repeat block with the input being the number of circles.
And since we entered in five, as the input for our function is going to repeat all this code five times
and the code is this move and turn which basically creates the circle.
So seeing this in action here, our cat asks how many circles we want.
Let's say three.
And as you can see our cat draws three circles just like that.
The only problem we do have is that we can't see them all as it's all in the same area.
So let's upgrade this function a bit.
Thirsty.
We will put the pin up so it doesn't draw everywhere.
Then we'll have our cat go to a random position.
Then we can put the pen back down.
And lastly we can have it change the pen color by ten.
And also it's just erase all when we start.
So giving this another go let's enter for and well that's not quite right I had is doing the same thing.
And well our problem is all this code should be inside our repeat block.
So moving it inside like so and giving it another go.
How many circles.
Let's say seven.
And slowly but surely, as you can see, our cat draws seven circles and it also draws each circle a
different color.
Now remember how I said functions are so useful because we can just write the code once and use it over
and over and over.
Well, if you look at this code, while the function is very useful as it makes our code very easy to
understand and manage, as we can see clearly what is going on, we are asking a question and then we
are drawing a certain number of circles, but we aren't really using this function to its full advantage
because, well, we are only calling it once.
So let's say in our program, we wanted our cat to draw a circle if we clicked on it because we have
this function, well, that's simple to do.
We can just grab this when the sprite is clicked block.
Then we can just say draw circle and enter one.
Now clicking play.
How many circles?
Let's say two.
Okay.
After that's done.
Now if we click the cat, it draws a circle.
Nice.
And also, let's say we wanted to make our circle smaller.
For some reason we can just go into our function, change the move to say five steps.
Now clicking play entering in one it draws a smaller circle.
But also if we click the cat, it also draws the smaller circle.
So as you can see, using this function ensures our code is consistent and it's easy to manage and easy
to use.
Now that's the power of functions.
But before I end, if you want to have fun with this, hold down shift while you click the flag and
you will see it goes into turbo mode.
And then if we enter a crazy value like 100,000, our cat goes absolutely crazy drawing circles.
So have some art fun with that.